<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the King at White-Hall on January the 30th, 1681 by Henry Maurice ...</title>
            <author>Maurice, Henry, 1648-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50342</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1370</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3724</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13675419</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13675419</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101230</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50342)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101230)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 794:41)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the King at White-Hall on January the 30th, 1681 by Henry Maurice ...</title>
                  <author>Maurice, Henry, 1648-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 35 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Samuel Roycroft for Robert Clavell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Published by His Majesties special command."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Isaiah XXXVII, 3 --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101230:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before the KING AT WHITE-HALL, ON JANUARY the 30<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, 1681.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> HENRY MAURICE, <hi>B. D. Chaplain to His Grace the Lord Archbiſhop of</hi> CANTERBURY.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by His Majeſties Special Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Samuel Roycroft,</hi> for <hi>Robert Clavell</hi> at the <hi>Peacock</hi> in S. <hi>Pauls Church-yard,</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:101230:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101230:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>ISAIAH XXXVII. 3.</bibl>
                  <p>This is a day of Trouble, of Rebuke, and Blaſphemy.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was the manner of the Ancient Chriſtians to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Anniverſaries of their Martyrs, not with the mournful Rites of a Funeral, nor the dejectedneſs of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting and Humiliation, but as the days of their Birth and Coronation, with the higheſt expreſſions of Joy and Thanksgiving, with the ſame chearfulneſs and ſerenity that they had ſuffer'd. Nor could it be conceiv'd proper to remember them with Tears, whoſe happy condition was rais'd above the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and charity of the Church's Prayers; for thoſe glorious Spirits take ſanctuary un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Heavenly Altar, where no Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, no Sacriledge can invade them. Thoſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:101230:3"/>as the Fellow-ſufferers of Chriſt, have the ſpecial priviledge of immediate admiſſion into Paradiſe: and tho the paſſage be rough and boyſterous, yet the ſpeed and the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch is proportionable; and the Fire as it haſtens to deſtroy, becomes at the ſame time a ſwift and rapid Chariot to tranſport the Martyrs into glory. What wonder then, if when one Member be ſo eminently ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour'd, the whole body take occaſion to rejoyce with it?</p>
            <p>But beſides this recompence of the Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, which the Church was wont to congra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulate with a joyful Remembrance, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour done to Religion by thoſe who own'd it with their dying Confeſſions, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd it with their Blood, requir'd yet a far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Acknowledgment and Thankſgiving. For what were the Paſſions of the Martyrs, but ſo many Victories of the Chriſtian Faith, that proclaimed it to be ſtronger than Principalities and Powers: ſtronger than the Counſel and Indignation of Men: ſtronger than the deſires of Life, or Terrors of Death? By theſe Conqueſts was the Kingdom of Chriſt enlarged; by theſe Invincible Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:101230:3"/>was the perverſneſs of the Nations re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd. When Chriſtians knew how to die better than to diſpute, but none underſtood yet how to rebel for their Religion: What then can the Commemoration of theſe Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctories be, but the common Triumph of Chriſtianity?</p>
            <p>How then are we departed from this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and reaſonable Practice? How comes this black and melancholy appearance to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure, and as it were eclipſe this Day of our Royal Martyr? Is the Crown of Martyrdom now become leſs glorious? or, is it not at leaſt an equal recompence for the loſs of Earthly Kingdoms? or the Cauſe for which he ſuffer'd, the Cauſe of God, and of his People, was it not ſufficient to entitle him to the dignity of Martyrdom? This part ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of no ſuſpicion, for the Title of the Martyr, as it is more honourable, ſo it is no leſs clear and undoubted than that of the King: Nay, the Malice of his Enemies, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetick as that of <hi>Caiaphas,</hi> foretold this his heavenly Inauguration, and accompliſhed their own prediction, by making him <hi>a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Prince</hi> indeed.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:101230:4"/>
            <p>We bewail not him therefore at this time, but weep for our ſelves and for our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, ſtain'd with this Innocent and Royal Blood, which was ſhed not by the hands of a Pagan Invader (for ſo ſome of our Kings became Martyrs in the defence of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and their People) but by a new and unhear'd of Treaſon of his own Subjects. And had the Conſpiracy of a few deſperate Wretches prevail'd againſt him, the ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ſecreſie of the ſtroke might have been our Excuſe, and cover'd the Nation from the guilt and infamy of the Fact: But this Treaſon uſurp'd the name of the Senate and People of the Land; and as if the Fears and Aſtoniſhment of the Nation had been taken for their conſent and approbation, Murder was dreſt up in the form of Publick Execution, and the Coronation of the King was not more ſolemn, had hardly more Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctators than that of the Martyr. Had he fallen in the day of Battel by the blind and undiſcerning fury of Rebellion, or after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards in the dark receſſes of his Priſon; the reproach had been common to us with many other Nations: But this was the firſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101230:4"/>time that Treaſon affected to make it ſelf a Spectacle, and grew Impudent and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate enough to undergo the horrour and envy of a Publick Regicide. And not content to trample all Earthly Majeſty un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der foot, the name of God and of Religion, and what is our more peculiar diſgrace, of Reform'd and Proteſtant Religion, were brought to ſuffer together with our late So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign, while they were abus'd into a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to carry on, and to juſtifie the Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of this day.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the ſad Reaſons of our preſent affliction, that render the remembrance of this Martyrdom ſo bitter. Theſe are the Clouds that overcaſt the day, and give it ſo different an appearance from the Feaſts of the Ancient Martyrs. 'Tis this in fine which renders it ſo exactly agreeable to the deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of the day in the Text; <hi>A day of Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, of Rebuke, and Blaſphemy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Trouble,</hi> as St. <hi>Jerom</hi> explains theſe words, belongs to us whoſe was the loſs, whoſe was the ſin. The <hi>Rebuke</hi> proceeds from God, whoſe Judgment this was. The <hi>Blaſphemy</hi> is the part of our Enemies, who are
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101230:5"/>glad of this occaſion to inſult us and our Religion. It is the Echo and repercuſſion of that execrable ſtroke, return'd upon us with the cenſures and reproaches of the World. Of theſe I ſhall ſpeak ſeverally, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the order of the Text, and begin with the <hi>Trouble of the day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">(1.) Of all the Bleſſings God is pleaſed to beſtow upon a Nation, there is none either more beneficial or more magnificent than a good King; who repreſents not only the Authority of the Univerſal Monarch, but the affection and tenderneſs of our Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father; and is the Image of the love and goodneſs, no leſs than of the Power and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of God. What happineſs may not a People enjoy under a Prince after Gods own heart? How muſt Religion flouriſh under his protection? how muſt Vertue reign in his Laws, and triumph in his Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? what Peace and Proſperity muſt adorn his Reign? what Security and Content muſt poſſeſs his Subjects, whoſe Power is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to ſecure them againſt foreign depreda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and whoſe Juſtice and Clemency in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſe between them and the Terrours of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101230:5"/>his own Power? This Condition of all things ſeems to approach neareſt to that of Gods Heavenly Kingdom, where the Saints do not Obey ſo much, as Reign together with their King. But when it ſhall pleaſe God to recall this great Inſtrument of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Welfare; when this mighty Veſſel, that contained ſo many, and ſuch variety of Bleſſings, ſhall be drawn up again into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and this Earthly God comes to die like other Men, the Joy and Delights of the People expire with him; and it is not an ordinary Affliction and Mourning that he leaves behind him, nor is any Loſs lamented with more ſincere or more obſtinate Tears. The Heathen were ſo ſenſible of this Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that to relieve themſelves they ran head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long into Idolatry, and chang'd their Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance into Adoration. Nor would they be perſwaded, that the beſt of their Kings did Die like one of the Common People, but that Death made them Inviſible and Divine: neither would they be comforted otherwiſe than by this perſwaſion, That they ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained under the Government and Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of their belov'd Princes. Thus <hi>Aſſyria,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101230:6"/>Egypt,</hi> and almoſt all the Nations of the Earth were firſt diſtracted into Superſtition, and the People of <hi>Rome</hi> would not be ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied for the loſs of their firſt King, before the Senate had decreed Worſhip, for him they were ſuſpected to have deſtroy'd. Nay, ſometimes this <hi>Trouble</hi> grew too ſtrong for all the amuſements of Superſtition; and <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyris,</hi> notwithſtanding the Opinion of his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, was remembred with perpetual La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations.</p>
            <p>But be this the Extravagance, and Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Heathen Zeal. Even the People of God himſelf were not above the reach of this <hi>Trouble;</hi> and though they were taught, that the ſame Providence did always watch over them under all the differences of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, yet they could not ſuſtain the loſs of a good Prince without ſome jealouſie, that God was going to deſert them; at leaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, not without ſingular Trouble and Affliction. <hi>When</hi> Moſes, <hi>the Great Prince of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>whoſe mighty Scepter commanded the Sea, and made it a Bulwark and Defence for his People on the Right hand, and on the Left; in whoſe time plenty came down from Heaven in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:101230:6"/>Bread and Fleſh, and Rivers ran in dry places;</hi> Moſes, <hi>the prodigy of Wiſdom and Modeſty, of great <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, and greater Miſtruſt of it; ſlow indeed of Speech, but wonderful in his Writings;</hi> Moſes, <hi>the Meekeſt Man upon Earth, eaſie to forgive Injuries (and happy were it, if the ſame Vertue that is ſo forward to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, could as eaſily reclaim the Offender;) eaſie in the Conceſſion of his own Prerogatives, and ſharing his Authority with the Elders of the Congregation; Such a Prince in ſhort, whoſe Government had more in it of the Father, than the King:</hi> When he came to take his leave of the People in order to go to the place where he muſt die, with how ſad a Countenance, with what diſcontented Murmuring was he anſwer'd? He found their Affection now more querulous and ungovernable than all their former Seditions. And tho <hi>Corah</hi> and his Faction had repreſented him odiouſly, as one that affected Arbitrary Dominion, yet when he came to Die, ſuch was the Peoples reſentments of that Loſs, that God ſeem'd to grow Jealous, and to miſtruſt their Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions towards Himſelf, and therefore thought fit to conceal him by a private
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101230:7"/>Interment at ſome diſtance from the Camp, on a high Hill, from whence is the faireſt Proſpect over all the Land of <hi>Canaan.</hi> Nor could all this prevent the Grief and Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of <hi>Iſrael</hi> for ſo great a Loſs; for, notwithſtanding they were upon the point of taking poſſeſſion of the Promis'd Land yet, they deſerred to accept the fruit of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty years labour and expectation, till they had paid a Sorrowful Duty to the Memory of <hi>Moſes,</hi> whom they bewayl'd Thirty Days in an extraordinary manner; and <hi>Joſephus</hi> adds, that they were never ſo much afflicted for any loſs.</p>
            <p>JOSIAH, <hi>the good, but unfortunate King of</hi> Judah, <hi>who had repayr'd the Temple of the Lord in</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>and reſtor'd the neglected and prophan'd Service of God into its ancient Purity and Splendor, having been unhappily ſlain in</hi> Megiddo, was lamented in an Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſual manner by the Inhabitants of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> nor was the Mourning en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded within the accuſtomed time, but tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to Poſterity. Jeremiah <hi>lamented for</hi> Joſiah, <hi>and all the Singing Men and Singing Women ſpake of</hi> Joſiah <hi>in their Lamentations
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101230:7"/>unto this day, and made it an Ordinance in</hi> Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael. And after the Return of the Captivity from <hi>Babylon,</hi> when one would think that all their former Sorrows had been forgot, yet this Grief was ſtill freſh and undiminiſh'd; and the Prophet <hi>Zachary,</hi> when he would have deſcribed the Mourning of the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Bride-Chamber, when Chriſt their Bridgroom ſhould be taken from them, could not find a greater Inſtance than that for <hi>Joſiah: It ſhall be like the Mourning of</hi> Hadadrimmon <hi>in the Valley of</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giddo.</p>
            <p>But this is the leaſt part of our preſent Trouble, nor would it be juſt to remember that Loſs with ſo much Affliction, which God hath long ſince ſo gloriouſly repair'd: Had our late Sovereign therefore dy'd the death of <hi>Moſes</hi> or <hi>Joſiah,</hi> and the courſe of Nature, or the chance of War, or any thing elſe than our own Sin and Madneſs depriv'd us of ſo great a Bleſſing, the Trouble of this Day might have ceas'd before this time: but when we conſider the Manner, and the Hands by which He fell, His Blood (like that of Murder'd Perſons, upon the approach of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101230:8"/>the Murderer) ſeems to run ſtill afreſh, and to fly in the face of this Guilty Nation, threatning it with yet more ſevere Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. For if the Sin of <hi>Corah,</hi> which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded no farther than Inſolent Expreſſions againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> (the loweſt ſtep of this days guilt, and ſcarcely to be reckon'd in the Computation of it) was puniſh'd with Fire and Peſtilence; How much ſorer Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſhall we expect, whoſe oblique Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of Authority was ſoon improv'd into open Inſolence, and (ſince no Faction did ever Inſult a Prince they did not mean to deſtroy) that Inſolence was aſſerted by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, and this carried on through Rapin, and Devaſtation, and Blood? And the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of that Rebellion rendring it ſtill more daring and wicked, the Guilt grew up with wonderful Increaſe, and exceeded all Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation and the Power of Diſcourſe; for who can expreſs the ſucceeding Treatment of Captiv'd Majeſty, the Indignities of His Impriſonment, of His Trial, of His Death, but with Tears, unleſs the greatneſs of the Trouble intercept even thoſe Expreſſions? Who can reflect upon ſo barbarous a Fact
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101230:8"/>without the greateſt diſorder and tumult of Thoughts? And now, if we yet retain any thing of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nature and Affections, How can we look upon this Land thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fil'd with Royal Blood, and laden with ſuch crying Aggravations, and not weep over it? How can we reflect upon the Singula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of this Guilt, and not be troubled with the apprehenſion of ſome Exemplary Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, as new and ſingular as the Crime?</p>
            <p>But why are We concern'd in this Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, who have no ſhare in the Guilt? For how many here preſent may juſtly boaſt their Services to that Excellent Prince, and the honour of Suffering with him? How many here preſent are the Noble Off-ſpring of that brave, but unfortunate Loyalty, that contended ſo long with a Proſperous Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, with unequal Force? How many more are wholly unconcerned in the Sin, who were yet unborn when this accurſed thing was committed? Yet none above the reach of this Trouble, none beyond the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of this Humiliation: For Publick Sins of ſuch Example and Scandal as this,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101230:9"/>like the firſt Rebellion of Man, may remain a Debt upon Poſterity, and involve more in the unhappy Conſequences of it than the <hi>Seed of the Evil Doers.</hi> For when God upon this Occaſion comes to reckon with a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and to call all their Sins to Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, who can endure the Viſitation? <hi>Noah,</hi> and <hi>Job,</hi> and <hi>Daniel,</hi> may ſave their own Souls indeed by their Righteouſneſs in ſuch General Calamities; but few, I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid will be able to make uſe of their Plea, and ſtand upon their Righteouſneſs and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity. They were but few, in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the whole Body of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that were immediately concern'd in putting our Saviour to Death: they were not many, and perhaps but a Mercenary Rabble, that Petition'd for his Crucifixon, and undertook to Anſwer all the Appeals of His Blood at their own, and their Childrens peril; yet when the time of their Viſitation came, (which was not till Forty years after the Killing of their King, when moſt of his Betrayers and Murderers were dead) every Age, and Sex, and Family, did ſhare alike in the Common Calamity, and the Famine,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101230:9"/>and Peſtilence, and Swords of the <hi>Romans,</hi> had no Commiſſion to diſtinguiſh; only the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> are ſaid to have eſcaped: And leſt We might preſume, and grow ſecure with this Example, we muſt remember, that the holineſs of their Lives was no leſs won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful than their Preſervation. And if the <hi>Poſt-nati,</hi> ſuch as had yet done neither Good nor Evil, may have reaſon to apprehend the Conſequence of this Day, the Remains of the Laſt Generation cannot be unconcern'd in this Trouble; for they were all in ſome meaſure Acceſſory to this Evil; and if they were not the Inſtruments, yet were they the Occaſion of what we now bewail, and by contributing every one his part to the general Provocation, help'd to draw down this heavy Judgment upon us. Many, whoſe Arms and Affection waited upon the Royal Standard, fought againſt it more effectually by their Sins; and like the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers of <hi>Ptolomy,</hi> the laſt of that Race, while they follow'd their purſu'd King, ſunk the Veſſel on which he was Embarqu'd. In ſhort, All had joyn'd to provoke the Wrath of God, and Fanatick Fury was but the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:101230:10"/>to Execute it. Therefore we will no longer regard thoſe wretched Authors of this Cruelty, whoſe Memory is as odious and abhorr'd, as the Prophane Reliques of their Carcaſſes; but we will look a little far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into the Nature of this Calamity, and in God's permiſſion of ſo barbarous, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Wickedneſs, read the ſeverity of his Judgment, and the ſharpneſs of his <hi>Rebuke,</hi> the Second Part of this Days Character. It is <hi>a day of Rebuke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. As it is a high Preſumption to Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret all the Acts of Providence, and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian to reſolve every Calamity into a Judgment; yet on the other ſide there are ſome ſo remarkable, ſo manifeſt Inſtances of Gods Indignation, that there needs no Hand-writing nor Prophet to explain them. There may be a mighty Wind, and yet God may not be in that Wind; there may be a Fire and Earthquakes, and God be in nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them: But when Fire and Brimſtone ſhall come down from Heaven to deſtroy Wicked Cities, Fire as prodigious and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural as the Luſts that kindled it; when an Earthquake, which is a kind of Sedition
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:101230:10"/>in nature, ſhall overwhelm the Seditious <hi>Corah</hi> and his Accomplices, and ſingle them from the reſt of the Congregation of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> there is no room either for Infidelity that believes nothing, or for Charity that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves all things, to diſpute ſuch Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Gods Judgments. Nor may we underſtand the <hi>Rebuke</hi> of God only from ſuch Acts of his immediate and flaming Hand; but many of thoſe Judgments which are Executed by the hands of Men are no leſs manifeſt. But of all the Evil Symptoms of God's Diſpleaſure towards a Nation, there are few more certain, or more fatal, than the Murmuring and Sedition of the People. And tho this may be of leſs Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence when it is natural, and the effect of Tyranny or Oppreſſion: yet when it is without Reaſon, and all hope and proſpect of Advantage; when it is as unaccountable as the Miſunderſtandings of <hi>Babel,</hi> like Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in a clear Sky, it is to be accounted a Prodigy, and the Voice of God. When the happieſt People on Earth, had They but a due ſence of their happineſs, ſecur'd with favourable Laws, and a more favourable
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101230:11"/>Prince: When a Nation Wealthy and Proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous, to the Envv of all their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, ſhall grow Diſcontented and Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous, fancy themſelves oppreſs'd; as Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulent Perſons imagine they are Hag-ridden: When they ſhall give themſelves up to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve Lies, as Incredible as they are Malicious, and affect a Change when they know not what to wiſh; we muſt conclude with <hi>Elias,</hi> that <hi>this Evil is from the Lord,</hi> and that his hand is in the Infatuation.</p>
            <p>But the Judgment of God may be yet more viſible in the ſucceſs of theſe Diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, from his permitting them to proceed to Extremities, to Acts of unuſual Violence and Cruelty. The Malice of the Devil, and the Wickedneſs of Men, are always contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Miſchief and Diſorder in the World; and that their Deſigns do not take effect, is owing to thoſe Inviſible Chains of Divine Providence, that checks and reſtrains them. Therefore whenever theſe Furies are let looſe, and permitted (for they need no other Commiſſion) to deſtroy without Controul; whatſoever Ravage they commit, we muſt impute not ſo much to their Malice, which
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:101230:11"/>is always the ſame, as to the removal of the Divine Protection; and look upon the Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of their Cruelty, as the Execution of ſome Secret Judgment pronounc'd upon us. But the Divine Judgment is never more remarkable, than when he gives way and permiſſion to ſuch things as he moſt of all deteſts, and caſts away without regard ſuch things as were wont to be moſt dear to him: ſo that where Treachery and Falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, where impudent and fulſom Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, when Perjury and Rebellion come to prevail and triumph over a Righteous Cauſe, there Wrath, we may be ſure, is come to the uttermoſt: When God has recourſe to ſuch odious Inſtruments of our Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment as theſe, the more vile or wicked they are, the more plain and more grievous is the Judgment. They that are overcome by the force of an Ambitious Conqueror, are a Lions Prey, and fall by a Noble Fury; but for a great and generous People to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the portion of Foxes, to be devour'd like <hi>Jezabel</hi> by ſordid and Domeſtick Fury, to be made a Sacrifice to Hypocrites and Apes, the ridiculous Counterfeit and Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſque
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:101230:12"/>of Men and Chriſtians, is to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd with the moſt Inſolent <hi>Blaſphemers of God,</hi> mention'd in the Second <hi>Pſalm,</hi> not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with the <hi>fierceneſs of his Wrath,</hi> but with <hi>his Contempt and Deriſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But when God <hi>ſhall forſake the Tabernacle in</hi> Shilo, <hi>and the Tent he has pitch'd among Men;</hi> when he ſhall deliver up Religion, and Royal Majeſty, the moſt Sacred things on Earth, to the Inſolence of Treaſon and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge, it is too clear, that he is <hi>wroth with his Inheritance.</hi> It is no Common Event; it is no Caſual concourſe of things; but by the Common Conſent of Mankind, it is the manifeſt <hi>Rebuke</hi> and Judgment of God.</p>
            <p>The Heathen fancy'd ſometimes, that they had fix'd their gods ſo ſurely to the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and Altars dedicated to their Honour, that it was not in their power to forſake thoſe Places of Sacrifice and Incenſe: But yet, when the Temples themſelves were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy'd by Lightning, and the Altars and Images were ſtruck from Heaven, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to apprehend, that the Indignation of the gods againſt the Wickedneſs of the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:101230:12"/>Worſhippers, might prevail over all their affection and fondneſs to the Place and Rites of their Worſhip. And the <hi>Jews</hi> thought God ſo wedded to their Church and Nation, that it was not poſſible for him utterly to forſake them: For how could he relinquiſh his People whom he had Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, <hi>the Seed of</hi> Abraham <hi>his Friend?</hi> How could he forſake the <hi>Ark of the Covenant,</hi> and the <hi>Law</hi> written with his own hands? How could he caſt away the Crown of <hi>David,</hi> which he had promis'd to preſerve to his Poſterity in a perpetual Succeſſion? How could he abandon the <hi>Houſe</hi> called by his own Name, the moſt happy Magnificent Habitation he had upon Earth? Or, could he forget all theſe things, yet ſurely he could not forget Himſelf; his Honour was ſo far engag'd, he muſt for his own ſake preſerve what he had eſtabliſh'd. But if all theſe Conſiderations are neglected, and this <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> together with their <hi>Religion,</hi> come to fall under the Feet of Heathen Oppreſſors, and all thoſe Holy Things in which they truſted come to be carried away, to adorn the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs of <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> or <hi>Roman</hi> Idols, the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:101230:13"/>Judgment is then as manifeſt as the Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, and the Wrath of God becomes a bright and ſhining, as well as a <hi>Conſuming Fire:</hi> Nor can the Provocation be ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, when God takes ſuch Extreme Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions as theſe, againſt all the Reluctance and Contradiction of his own Goodneſs. <hi>Thou art</hi> Gilead <hi>unto me, and the top of</hi> Leba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non; <hi>but I will make thee a Wilderneſs, and Cities without Inhabitant;</hi> and in another place, Tho the King of <hi>Judah, were the Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net on my Right hand, yet would I pluck him off.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet all former Inſtances of Divine Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſeem to be ſurpaſs'd by the <hi>Rebuke</hi> of this Day: when the World, that was grown Old under the Tautologies of <hi>Sin,</hi> and the Circulations of repeated <hi>Judgments,</hi> was ſurpriz'd with a New thing, which it could not have imagin'd, either that Men ſhould ever be ſo wicked as to Attempt, or God ſo angry as to Permit. For <hi>this Day,</hi> a holier Religion than that reveal'd to <hi>Moſes,</hi> was expos'd to Contempt and Deriſion; and a Church more dear to God than that of the <hi>Jews,</hi> given up to Sacriledge and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:101230:13"/>Oppreſſion; a Church honour'd with the firſt Royal Defender of the Chriſtian Faith; preſerv'd amidſt the Corruptions of the World, and the Contradictions of <hi>Hereſie</hi> and <hi>Schiſm;</hi> a Church lately Reſcu'd from the Ruſt of a tedious <hi>Superſtition,</hi> and the Tyranny of an Inſolent and Powerful <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtor.</hi> And what is more ſingular, both in the Puniſhment, and the Sin, the Head, the Mortal and Earthly Head of this Church, an Orthodox and Holy Prince, whoſe Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues rais'd him higher above the People than his Throne, and the leaſt of whoſe Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles was that of a KING; Such a King, ſuch a Man, was this day given up a Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, to a prevailing <hi>Rebellion;</hi> and as a Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice led in Proceſſion thrô pretended Courts, and the formalities of a Proceſs, thrô in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Indignities, to a Solemn and Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious Slaughter. <hi>Paſs over to the Iſles of</hi> Chittim, <hi>and ſee: go unto</hi> Kedar, <hi>and conſider diligently, and ſee whether there be any ſuch thing.</hi> And we may Anſwer in the words of <hi>Joel, There never was any ſuch thing, nor ever ſhall be.</hi> And as the firſt part is ſufficiently veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fi'd in the Singularity of this Judgment: ſo
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:101230:14"/>We beſeech God the Promiſe may belong to us too, <hi>That there never may be any ſuch thing;</hi> and that God would put his <hi>Bow</hi> in the Clouds, and declare, <hi>That he would never deſtroy us after this manner any more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, tho the Loſs may be Repair'd, and the Guilt done away by Repentance and Pardon; tho Judgment may turn again into Mercy, and the Terrors of this <hi>Rebuke</hi> ceaſe; yet who can waſh away the Reproach and Infamy? who can ſilence the <hi>Blaſphemy</hi> of this Day? which is the Laſt Part of the Character of the Day, <hi>It is a Day of Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation had been long held in ſingular Reputation, for good Natur'd and Loyal Courage; and not only the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Nations, but the more remote Parts of the Earth have been Witneſſes of Their Dutiful Affection to their Kings, whom they follow'd in their Expeditions with forward and unwearied Duty. But alas! the <hi>Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy</hi> of this Day has ſilenc'd all our Ancient Praiſe, and the Stains of this <hi>Royal Blood</hi> has Blemiſh'd all the Glories of our former Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty; and that Name which was once the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:101230:14"/>Praiſe and the Dread of the Nations, by <hi>this Act</hi> became a Proverb of <hi>Reproach,</hi> a <hi>Deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and a <hi>Hiſſing</hi> among all People: Nay, We our ſelves were almoſt aſham'd of it, nor could we own the Name of <hi>Engliſh</hi> without Diſtinction or Excuſe, without Diffidence and Bluſhing. And, what was there once left of the <hi>Name</hi> that we could own? the Honour and Majeſty of it had been Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniouſly put to Death with our Martyr'd Sovereign; and the Sordid name of <hi>Common Wealth</hi> had defac'd the Royal Image and Inſcription of our <hi>Ancient Monarchy:</hi> nor could we tell our ſelves whoſe the Vile Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſcription was, and could not but be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maz'd with our own <hi>Blaſphemy</hi> and Degra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of our ſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> willing to give ſome check to the Importunate Malice of the <hi>Jews,</hi> who demanded the Crucifixion of our Lord, puts this harſh and diſhonourable Queſtion to them, <hi>Shall I Cruciſie your King?</hi> That Name contains, if not always the whole Power and Authority, yet at leaſtwiſe all the Honour and Dignity of a People: He cannot be Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifi'd, but Your Name muſt be Crucifi'd
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:101230:15"/>with him in the Inſcription of his Titles. This was a Wickedneſs too great for the tender Conſciences of <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> directly to own: This was a Diſhonour <hi>Jews</hi> could not digeſt; <hi>then,</hi> and ever ſince, the moſt Vile and Abject Race of Human Kind: Wherefore they firſt Diſown him, and then deſire he ſhould be Crucifi'd; <hi>We have no King but Caeſar,</hi> and therefore cannot be concern'd in the Diſgrace of this Perſon. And their <hi>Ignorance</hi> was their Excuſe; They had never ſubmitted to the Government of Chriſt; they never underſtood his Title. But the <hi>Blaſphemy</hi> of this Day receives none of theſe Excuſes; here can be no plea of <hi>Ignorance</hi> or <hi>Miſtake:</hi> The Superſcription of the Croſs is here own'd, as well as the Crucifixion; and the Treaſon was grown too Impudent and Vainglorious to diſſemble or extenuate. And now, all that we can anſwer to this <hi>Blaſphemy,</hi> is, but <hi>Repentance</hi> and <hi>Reſtitution,</hi> or rather the <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Compaſſion of GOD,</hi> who has reſtor'd Us to our Ancient Honour and Dignity, by the Reſtauration of our <hi>Gracious Sovereign.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:101230:15"/>
            <p>And tho all this Reproach and Obloquy may be juſtly come upon us, yet what has our Innocent and Holy <hi>Religion</hi> done to be Involv'd in the ſame <hi>Blaſphemy?</hi> The reſt of the Calamity was grievous enough, and like the <hi>Arrows of God</hi> ſticking in the Fleſh; but this breaks the Bones, according to the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of the Royal Pſalmiſt, <hi>My Bones are ſmitten aſunder, as with a Sword: while mine Enemies that hate me, caſt me in the Teeth.</hi> Nor was it any Perſonal Reproach that wounded him ſo deep, but the Diſhonour of God: <hi>Namely, while they daily ſay unto me, Where is now thy God?</hi> And I would to God, the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of our Religion had wanted ſo fair an occaſion to <hi>Blaſpheme</hi> it: juſt, there can be none; and this is but too plauſible. For, when <hi>Religion</hi> was made the Diſguiſe of a moſt Unnatural Treaſon; and the moſt Wicked Wretches upon Earth did Impropriate to themſelves the Name of <hi>Saints,</hi> together with all the Sacred Functions of the <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> and took a ſingular delight in the ſtyle of a <hi>Preaching</hi> and <hi>Praying People:</hi> When <hi>Prayer</hi> and <hi>Faſting</hi> was made the Prologue to ſome Bloody Tragedy, and ſerv'd as the Eve or
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:101230:16"/>Vigil to the Day of Sacrifice: When <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture</hi> was alledg'd in Defence of the greateſt Villanies, even that of this Day; and where Scripture could not be colourably <hi>perverted, Immediate Revelation</hi> was pretended, and <hi>Special Commiſſion</hi> from God: In ſum, When all the Miſchiefs which We now bewail, were carried on under the diſguiſe of <hi>Conſcience</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> what wonder is it if the <hi>Name of God,</hi> upon this occaſion, <hi>be Blaſphemed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Gentiles?</hi> Great and grievous was the <hi>Blaſphemy,</hi> and too fatal was the Influence it had upon Weak Minds, that had been Trayn'd up in the Opinion of <hi>Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</hi> Many began to run away from all Form and Appearance of Religion, and were afraid to make any ſhew of <hi>Piety,</hi> for fear of being ſuſpected for <hi>Rebels</hi> and <hi>Impoſtors:</hi> Many were aſham'd of that Profeſſion that was cover'd with ſo much <hi>Infamy</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach;</hi> and <hi>True Piety</hi> was almoſt out of Countenance, and forc'd to hide it ſelf. Yet, after all this, The <hi>Blaſphemies of Irreligion</hi> are but falſe, and miſtaken Triumphs. For if a True Jewel loſe nothing of its Value, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there are many Counterfeits; if the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:101230:16"/>ſincere and precious Metal preſerve its E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem, notwithſtanding all ſecret practice to Embaſe it; If an <hi>Angel of Light</hi> cannot loſe his Integrity and Honour, becauſe <hi>Satan</hi> transforms himſelf into his Likeneſs; why ſhould <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi> why ſhould <hi>Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> and <hi>Vertue</hi> ſuffer for the Wickedneſs of detected <hi>Hypocriſie?</hi> Nay, on the contrary, it is clear, that the Real Value of any thing makes Men ſo induſtrious to Counterfeit; and if there were not ſome great Excellency in <hi>True Godlineſs,</hi> Evil men would never take the pains to purſue the Shadow of it, and to carry on their Wicked Deſigns under that Diſguiſe.</p>
            <p>But, beſides the Common Enemies of <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi> the Peculiar Adverſaries of the <hi>Reformation</hi> are not wanting to ſo fair an Occaſion of <hi>Blaſpheming</hi> it. The Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which we charg'd but too truly with the Treaſonable Doctrine of <hi>Killing Kings,</hi> and Practices correſpondent, do not neglect to return the Charge with Inſolence and Triumph, and appeal to this day for the Loyalty of <hi>Proteſtant Religion.</hi> It cannot but be a great grief to any one, who owns
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:101230:17"/>the leaſt Affection to that Name, under which ſo many Noble Churches united againſt the Common Oppreſſour, that any who make Profeſſion of it, ſhould give the Enemy ſo great occaſion to <hi>Blaſpheme.</hi> But Men will take what Appellations they pleaſe, and Act afterwards as they think fit; and it would be too hard meaſure to charge the Crimes of ſome Uſurpers upon the whole Denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: the Lewdneſs of the <hi>Gnoſticks</hi> might have been as reaſonably charg'd upon <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity;</hi> and the Piracy which the <hi>Turks</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe under the Counterfeit of our <hi>Colours,</hi> may with the ſame Juſtice be imputed to Us. And this is our Comfort in the preſent Caſe, That whatever Agreement the <hi>Authors</hi> of this Days Wickedneſs may own with other Churches, they have done us the Favour to diſown Us. And doubtleſs We have great Reaſon to own the Kindneſs of their <hi>Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</hi> They went out from Us, and would not be of Us; becauſe Our Doctrine was too Loyal and Paſſive for Men of ſo fiery Temper: and the greateſt Tyranny they found in Our Religion, was the Reſtraint that it laid on the <hi>Conſcience</hi> of Men from
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:101230:17"/>reſiſting againſt the <hi>Higher Powers:</hi> This was, nay is yet, more grievous to them than all the pretended Oppreſſions of the <hi>Hierarchy;</hi> This is a more real and greater grievance to their Conſciences than all the <hi>Rites</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies</hi> of the Church: And had they been Enemies only to the Dignity of our Church, or the Decence of our Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, ſome Accommodation might be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected; but alaſs, theſe things are but Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, to cover the Reſtleſs and the Factious Spirit, and to diſguiſe their Practices a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Government. 'Tis <hi>this</hi> we know not how to reconcile to our Communion; 'Tis <hi>this</hi> which no honeſt Comprehenſion can admit: Nor is this a new Charge rais'd by Zealots of Our Church to render them odious to the Government: For a Great Stateſman of this Nation, and reputed no Ill Friend to the Party, has long ago acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Us from any note of <hi>Perſecution</hi> on their Account, and confeſſes Their <hi>Sedition</hi> to have been the ſole ground of all thoſe Laws that have been made againſt them; and adds, in behalf of the Government then, <hi>That it was Wiſe enough to diſtinguiſh between
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:101230:18"/>Conſcience and Faction.</hi> And how much Wiſer, at leaſtwiſe more Knowing in that Point, ſad Experience has made us ſince, I need not ſay, <hi>This Day</hi> ſhall ſpeak it for me.</p>
            <p>But now to Return to the <hi>Blaſphemy</hi> of the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> If Community of Name be not ſo much to be regarded, as Agreement in Doctrine, our Accuſers will be found to have a greater part in theſe <hi>Sectaries,</hi> than We; for both Agree in the Fundamentals of <hi>Rebellion,</hi> and the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs and Merit of <hi>Reſiſting the Higher Powers.</hi> And if we Trace backward the Footſteps of our <hi>Troubles,</hi> we may eaſily ſee, that it was from thence the <hi>Faction</hi> bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row'd their Arguments; and from their <hi>Catholick Authors,</hi> the Semons and Speeches of the <hi>Party,</hi> had deriv'd all the Art and Colour of Their <hi>Treaſon.</hi> But, this is not a Time to Juſtifie, but to Humble our ſelves; nor is it ſo material, from whence theſe Barbarous Men deriv'd their Principles of <hi>Diſloyalty,</hi> ſince it is too certain that they owe all their Succeſs and Advantages to our Sins; as theſe Increaſe, ſo do They; they
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:101230:18"/>have both one Common Fate, they mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply and decreaſe together. Our <hi>Propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> and <hi>Contempt of Religion,</hi> begets in them a <hi>Contempt of Authority</hi> and the <hi>Laws;</hi> and the Neglect of that <hi>Holy Service</hi> we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to Extol, adds greater Numbers to our Enemies, than all their Arts and Induſtry can pervert. If we would weaken that <hi>Faction,</hi> let us take away the Support they have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong our ſelves, the <hi>Open ſcandal</hi> and <hi>Vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of our Lives;</hi> and then they are leſt without Pretence, and fall without our Trouble. Let us confute their <hi>Reproaches</hi> by a Reformation of our <hi>Manners,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect their <hi>Hypocriſie,</hi> not by waſhing off the Paint with <hi>Satyr,</hi> but by Confronting their Pretence and Form with <hi>ſolid</hi> and <hi>ſincere Piety:</hi> Without this, all other Means will be to little purpoſe. Without this, <hi>Loyalty</hi> is but <hi>Affectation,</hi> a thing no leſs Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerviceable, than it will be Uncertain; for he who Fears not <hi>God,</hi> will have but little Reverence for a <hi>Man,</hi> whatever Title or Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority he may bear; and he who has no due Conſcience of his <hi>Duty to his Prince,</hi> and <hi>Obeys</hi> not for <hi>Gods ſake,</hi> but his Own, is a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:101230:19"/>but during his own Pleaſure or Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage: Or, if the Treacherous foundation do not betray that <hi>frail Faith</hi> to Change and Ruine, yet what Fruit can be hop'd from the Services of thoſe who are at defiance with GOD, upon whom all the Succeſs does de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend? <hi>Be not deceiv'd, God is not mock'd,</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially not by an open and profeſt <hi>Contempt:</hi> and if the different Mockeries of <hi>Hypocriſie</hi> and <hi>Prophaneſs</hi> ſhould come to Contend for Victory; who can tell, but that God ſhould rather Incline to favour the Shadow and Reſemblance of <hi>Religion,</hi> rather than a Wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton Contempt of all that is Sacred and Good; and that <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites of tranſparent Diſguiſe, may yet be preferr'd to <hi>Sadduces</hi> and <hi>Libertines,</hi> that <hi>believe neither a Spirit, nor a Reſurrection,</hi> and Live, as if neither <hi>Body</hi> nor <hi>Soul</hi> were to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der any Account? And now let us Learn from this <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nhappy Day,</hi> (and how ſhall we Learn, if <hi>this</hi> cannot Teach us) the Neceſſity of Joyning <hi>Religion</hi> to <hi>Loyalty,</hi> to <hi>Fear God and the King</hi> together. It is the ſame <hi>Power</hi> that is to be Reveronc'd in both, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſeparated but to the manifeſt Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:101230:19"/>of all Human Authority. Let us Laſtly, out of a due Senſe of the <hi>Trouble, Rebuke,</hi> and <hi>Blaſphemy of this Day,</hi> Learn, to deteſt all the plauſible Beginnings and Witchcrafts of <hi>Rebellion,</hi> and Confirm our ſelves with ſtedfaſt Reſolutions of perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual <hi>Obedience</hi> to our Sovereign: And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Since it is not the <hi>Affection</hi> and <hi>Loyalty</hi> of Men, but the <hi>Favour</hi> of GOD that ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports the <hi>Royal Throne;</hi> Let us Beſeech Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, That he would Protect the Perſon of his <hi>Anointed,</hi> and make the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment to Proſper in his Hands; that at length He would Recompence all the Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the <hi>Royal FATHER,</hi> with Double Bleſſings of <hi>Proſperity</hi> upon the <hi>SON,</hi> Our Dread Sovereign, that <hi>under him We may live Quiet and Peaceable Lives, in all Godlineſs and Honeſty,</hi> in all <hi>humble Obedience and Loyalty.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
